{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "These people lived in wharenui or big houses, some of which ban food inside. Nephrite jade weapons called punamu were used by these people, who built a defensive settlement, or Pa, at Mount Eden. Continuation of these people’s tikanga, or customs, may have led to devastating raids into the Bay of Plenty led by Hongi Hika with new found firearms. A subgroup of these people, the Moriori settled in the Chatham Islands, while the main group of these people signed the Treaty of Waitangi. For ten points, name these Polynesian indigenous people of New Zealand.",
      "answer": "The Maori people"
    },
    {
      "question": "This institution controversially withdrew from funding a poster of Ronald Haeberle’s photograph of the My Lai massacre with the overlaid caption “And babies.” In 2012, this institution added flOw, Canabalt, Myst, Katamari Damacy and ten other video games to its collection. Jasper Johns’ Flag, Marc Chagall’s I and the Village, and Picasso’s Les Demoiselles d’Avignon are part of the collection of, for ten points, what New York art museum that focuses on contemporary art and design?",
      "answer": "Museum of Modern Art or MoMA"
    },
    {
      "question": "This activist was sentence to one month of hard labor after assisting Amelia Brown in throwing a shoe at H. H. Asquith. In one photo, this woman is shown toasting with a glass of grape juice in front of a flag with two rows of stars on it. This woman organized a 1913 procession led by a crown-wearing Inez Milholland atop a white horse. With Crystal Eastman, this woman co-wrote an amendment that has yet to be adopted by the United States. The Equal Rights Amendment was drafted by, for ten points, what activist who, with Lucy Burns, founded the National Woman’s Party.",
      "answer": "Alice Stokes Paul"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man supposedly went into battle unprotected, believing that “the Lord God [was his] armor.” French aid in the Treaty of Barwalde allowed this man to launch an intervention in Germany. Chancellor Axel Oxenstierna ruled in place of this man after he was killed leading a cavalry charge at Lu¨tzen. This father of Christina became known as the “Lion of the North” after winning the Battle of Breitenfeld. For ten points, identify this king of Sweden during the Thirty Years’ War.",
      "answer": [
        "Gustavus Adolphus",
        "Gustav II Adolph,"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In Canada, sites for this project included the Eldorado Mine and Chalk River. Dupont’s P-9 Project produced substances for this project, for which Kenneth Nicholas helped buy pitchblende ore from the Belgian Congo. Washington’s Hanford Site was one complex operated by this project, whose final products were designed and tested at a site in New Mexico, Los Alamos. For ten points, name this Allied project to produce the atomic bomb.",
      "answer": "Manhattan Project"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the precursor to this case, Samuel Russell’s testimony was ruled hearsay and he hired Samuel Bay. In this case, 7 justices refused to abide by Marie Louise v. Marot despite the opinion of John McLean. Robert Cooper Grier was pressured by James Buchanan to side with the majority in this case. The majority decision in this case ruled that Congress cannot ban slavery in certain territories as it infringes on the right to property. For ten points, name this 1857 case in which Roger Taney ruled that an enslaved man was not free because he spent time in Wisconsin.",
      "answer": "Dred Scott v. Sandford"
    },
    {
      "question": "One historian described this government as “the past that will not pass” in a book about the memory of this government, titled its “Syndrome.” This government studied by Henry Rousso and Robert Paxton ran the Drancy internment camp and carried out the Vel d’Hiv roundup against its Jewish population. Formed after the Second Armistice at Compi´egne, for ten points, name this government led by Pierre Laval and Phillip P´etain which collaborated with the Nazis in WWII.",
      "answer": "Vichy France"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Dawn of Liberty monument in this country commemorates the 1986 Jeltoqsan riots. Its not Belarus, but a protocol signed in its former capital was a founding document of the Commonwealth of IndependentStates.Thiscountryishometoanucleartestsitenicknamed“ThePolygon”atSemipalatinsk and the world’s largest spaceport at Baikonur. In 2019, this country renamed its capital to Nur-Sultan. For ten points, name this country once led by Nursultan Nazarbayev from Astana.",
      "answer": "Kazakhstan"
    },
    {
      "question": "A racist and comically incompetent former owner of this team names a rule banning NBA teams from trading their first round draft pick from consecutive drafts. Current owner Dan Gilbert wrote a letter in Comic Sans stating that this team will “win an NBA championship before the self-titled former “King” wins one.” For ten points, name this team that drafted Anthony Bennett, Andrew Wiggins, and Kyrie Irving while its biggest star, LeBron James, took his four year sabbatical in Miami.",
      "answer": [
        "Cleveland Cavaliers",
        "either",
        "both names"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A leader at this location wrote a letter to “All Americans in the World” in which he claimed he was determined to die like a soldier. James Neill, appalled by the lack of supplies at this location, wrote to the provisional government saying “If there has ever been a dollar here I have no knowledge of it.” This location was said to be key to keeping “Bexar out of the hands of the enemy” in a letter by James Bowie who claimed its defense was necessary for the salvation of Texas. For ten points, name this mission in San Atonio that was besieged by Mexiacn forces.",
      "answer": "The Alamo"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This leader won the Battle of Shirimni during his campaigns against the Georgians. After the failed Siege of Sredets, this leader was nearly killed in the Battle of the Gates of Trajan. This leader founded the Varangian Guard after marrying his sister Anna to a foreign leader. This leader’s enemy Samuel suffered a heart attack after this leader blinded 99 of every 100 prisoners from the Battle of Kleidion. For ten points, name this Byzantine Emperor named for his victory over the Bulgarian empire.",
        "answer": [
          "Basil II",
          "Basil the Bulgar Slayer"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Basil’s sister Anna married this leader of the Kievan Rus, the son of Sviatoslav I of Kiev.",
        "answer": "Vladimir I"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Hobbes argued that complete submission to this model of government is necessary because humans are self-interested. Locke claimed that this model of government prevents a permanent state of war between individuals. One work titled after this model begins “man is born free, but everywhere is in chains” and argues that this model obeys the general will. For ten points, what model where citizens surrender some rights to legitimate government to guarantee others was written about by Rousseau?",
        "answer": [
          "The Social Contract",
          "monarchy",
          "absolutism until “prevents” BONUS:Agreeingtothesocialcontracttheoreticallyraisescivilsocietyoutofwhatkindofpre-government existence which was celebrated by Rousseau and in which life is described as “solitary, poor, nasty, brutish, and short” in Leviathan? ANSWER: The state of nature 3 Juhayman al-Otaybi carried out a terrorist attack in this city at a location that was under renovation by the Binladin group, leading French GIGN commandos to intervene. A Hashimite Sharif who controlled this city, Hussein, led the Arab Revolt and after the fall of the Ottoman Empire, proclaimed himself Caliph. This city’s Banu Quraish forces lost the Battle of Badr to Muslim forces from Medina. For ten points, name this birthplace of Muhammed, where pilgrims travel to do the Hajj. ANSWER: Mecca",
          "Makkah"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Mecca and Medina are located in this western region of Saudi Arabia that borders the Red Sea and whose largest city is Jeddah. In 1916, Hussein bin Ali declared himself the king of this region.",
        "answer": "Hejaz"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In one election, this Presidential candidate’s party was attacked by Samuel D. Burchard as the party of “Rum, Romanism, and Rebellion.” This politician won over a large number of Republican voters, which were then labeled mugwumps, due to his opponents stance on the spoils system. This man was accused of having an illegitimate child which led to the chant “Ma, Ma, where’s my Pa” to become a key part of the Election of 1884. For ten points, name this politician from Ohio, the only President to have served non-consecutive terms.",
        "answer": "Grover Cleveland"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Cleveland defeated this Republican candidate, depicted in cartoons as a tattooed man before artists, in the 1884 presidential election.",
        "answer": "James Blaine"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A piece in this style phases a 12 beat African bell rhythm between two performers. An aleatoric piece in this style contains 53 short phrases each to be repeated a random number of times. The development of this style is credited to La Monte Young. The “holy” type of this style is in works such as Tabula Rasa and Fur Alina by Arvo P¨art. One of the first works in this style is Terry Riley’s In C. For ten points, name this style of music that uses a limited set of material.",
        "answer": [
          "minimalism",
          "word forms"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This composer depicted the lives of Akhenaten, Albert Einstein, and Mahatma Gandhi in a set of three minimalist operas.",
        "answer": "Phillip Glass"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One incident in this region was sparked after John Dalrymple, Lord of Stair, refused to allow a deadline to pass. That incident in this region was defined as “slaughter under trust” and was the Glencoe Massacre. The Squadrone Volante helped pass legislation in this region which guaranteed the status of its Presbyterian Church and kept its laws but allowed this region to send peers to the House of Lords. Queen Anne united England with, for ten points, what northern neighbor?",
        "answer": [
          "Scotland",
          "Scottish Highlands before “Squadrone Volante”"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This set of two 1707 laws, one English and one Scottish, united the English and Scottish Parliaments and formed the Kingdom of Great Britain.",
        "answer": "1707 Acts of Union"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "William Yancey spearheaded a platform named for this state that held that the Federal government could not restrict slavery in territories. A ship named for this state was sunk at Cherbourg while under the command of Raphael Semmes and was the subject of a series of claims in which the United States demanded restitution from Great Britain. At a battle in this state, a Union commander ordered “Damn the torpedoes!” en-route to defeating Confederate forces at Mobile Bay. For ten points, name this state that, prior to it being moved to Richmond, hosted the Confederate capital at Montgomery.",
        "answer": "Alabama"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The order “Damn the torpedos!” was given by this Union admiral who, several years prior, led the capture of New Orleans.",
        "answer": "David Farragut"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During WWII, Japanese soldiers in this city perpetrated the Silver Mine Bay Massacre. In 1945, Japan surrendered this city to the HMS Switsure. Japan gained control over this city after the surrender of Governor Mark Atchinson Young. After WWII, this city’s 99-year lease was formally concluded during the rule of Deng Xiaoping. For the point, name this Chinese city-state that was given back to China in 1997 after the end of a British lease.",
        "answer": "Hong Kong"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Japanese invasion of Hong Kong occurred before Britain and Japan declared war and started four hours after this other Japanese surprise attack.",
        "answer": "Pearl Harbor"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Protesting the Vietnam War",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Boxer, known as “the Greatest,” whose refusal to fight in Vietnam led to a 1971 Supreme Court case.",
          "answer": "Muhammad Ali or Cassius Clay"
        },
        {
          "question": "August 1969 music festival in New York where several performers criticized the war.",
          "answer": "Woodstock"
        },
        {
          "question": "Arlington, Virginia office building that was marched on by 100,000 protesters in 1967.",
          "answer": "the Pentagon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Objects burned by anti-war protesters and made obsolete in 1973 when conscription was ended.",
          "answer": "draft cards"
        },
        {
          "question": "CBS newscaster who declared the US “mired in stalemate,” causing LBJ to lament “I’ve lost middle America.”",
          "answer": "Walter Cronkite"
        },
        {
          "question": "1969 Supreme Court case regarding the use of anti-war black armbands as free speech in public schools.",
          "answer": "Tinker v. Des Moines"
        },
        {
          "question": "Congresswoman who voted against declaring both World Wars and led a women’s pacifist march in 1968.",
          "answer": "Jeannette Rankin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Veteran-led public hearing in Detroit in early 1972 that sought to expose American war crimes.",
          "answer": "Winter Soldier Investigation"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Spanish Armada",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "English queen who the Spanish wanted to depose via the Armada.",
          "answer": "Elizabeth I"
        },
        {
          "question": "Type of weapon used by English “hellburners” to counter the Aramada.",
          "answer": [
            "fireships",
            "anything related to incendiary combat",
            "the ships were set ablaze and steered into the enemy fleet, where they exploded"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Religious affiliation of the wind that dispersed the Armada, according to the celebrating victors.",
          "answer": "Protestant wind"
        },
        {
          "question": "Year, within one, that the largest Armada sailed against England.",
          "answer": [
            "1588",
            "1587",
            "1589"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Speech given by the English queen to land troops; it notes “I have the heart and stomach of a king.”",
          "answer": "Tilbury speech"
        },
        {
          "question": "Small port near France where the Armada was defeated in its only major battle.",
          "answer": "Gravelines"
        },
        {
          "question": "Dukedom ruled by Alonso Perez de Guzman, who commanded the Armada.",
          "answer": "Duke of Medina Sidonia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Treaty signed by the English to help Dutch rebels at Antwerp; the enraged Spanish sent the Armada three years later.",
          "answer": "Treaty of Nonsuch"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Emperor Puyi",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Chinese dynasty that ended with Puyi’s overthrow.",
          "answer": "Qing Dynasty"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mandate to rule China, which Puyi lost after his deposition.",
          "answer": "Mandate of Heaven or Tianming"
        },
        {
          "question": "Beijing palace complex where he was allowed to remain.",
          "answer": [
            "Forbidden City",
            "Gugong",
            "Forbidden Palace"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Empress Dowager who chose Puyi as emperor at age 2.",
          "answer": "Cixi"
        },
        {
          "question": "Japanese puppet state where he was installed as a ruler in 1932.",
          "answer": "Manchukuo do not"
        },
        {
          "question": "1912 revolution that forced his abdication.",
          "answer": "Xinhai Revolution"
        },
        {
          "question": "Opponent of Puyi, a general who made himself emperor in 1915 and was the first President of the Republic of China.",
          "answer": "Yuan Shikai or Hongxian Emperor"
        },
        {
          "question": "General who restored Puyi to the throne for a little more than a week in 1917.",
          "answer": "Zhang Xun or Chang H’sun"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this period, James McGready organized Kentuckians at the Red River Meeting House. An illiterate speaker named “Black Harry” preached during this era. Barton Stone’s (20 pts)",
        "“New Lights” movement began during this period. Dispensationalism and Adventism began during this period. Charles Finney coined the term (10 pts)",
        "“burned-over district” for western New York during this period. This movement was led by Baptist and Methodist preachers and followed a similarly named movement in the 1730s. For 10 points, name this American religious movement that saw the birth of Mormonism."
      ],
      "answer": "Second Great Awakening"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This non-water deity was conflated with the Cretan goddess Britomartis. The destruction of a temple to this deity by Herostratus led to the expression (20 pts)",
        "“herostratic fame.” The Brauronia ceremony celebrated this deity. A temple to this deity was destroyed on the same day as Alexander the Great’s birth and was located in (10 pts)",
        "Ephesus. This deity sent a wild boar to kill Adonis and turned Actaeon’s hunting dogs against him after he saw her bathing. For 10 points, name this Greek goddess of the hunt, the twin sister of Apollo."
      ],
      "answer": "Artemis"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) John Barton was part of an influential twelve man society that advocated this goal. James Stephen was the legal expert of the Act of Parliament that brought about this goal. Efforts to accomplish this goal included the creation of medallion by Josiah Wedgwood that read (20 pts)",
        "“Am I Not a Man and a Brother?” James Oglethorpe became a close friend of (10 pts)",
        "Granville Sharp after reading the latter’s writings advocating for this goal. In 1792, a bill calling for this goal was brought before Parliament by William Wilberforce. Achieved in 1807, for ten points, name this goal of ending the abduction of West Africans into forced labor."
      ],
      "answer": "Abolition of the Slave trade in the British Empire"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A nativist leader of one of this country’s parties is nicknamed “The Captain” and belonged to its Young Padanians Movement as a youth. A populist party in this country is named for its principles of (20 pts)",
        "public water, sustainable transport and development, right to internet access, and environmentalism. That party was founded by a comedian and blogger who had previous led a “V-day” anti-corruption rally in 2007. This country’s (10 pts)",
        "Northern League and Five Star Party formed a government in 2018. For ten points, name this country home to Matteo Salvini and Beppe Grillo."
      ],
      "answer": "Republic of Italy"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) While serving as military governor of Bavaria, this man compared Nazis to Democrats and Republicans. This man “raced to Messina” against (20 pts)",
        "Bernard Montgomery after carrying out Operation Husky. This leader commanded the fictional First United States Army Group as part of (10 pts)",
        "Operation Fortitude. This general was temporarily removed from command after slapping two shell-shocked solders in 1943. Prior to Operation Overlord, this man gave a series of speeches to his Third Army. For ten points, name this American general nicknamed “Old Blood and Guts.”"
      ],
      "answer": "George S. Patton"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This ruler invited Alexander von Humboldt to probe his country’s mineral resources. This ruler told Karl von Ficquelmont that his country must look to the east after signing the Treaty of Hunkar Iskelesi with the Ottomans. Jozef Chlopicki’s (20 pts)",
        "November Uprising was brutally suppressed by this ruler, who lambasted the London Straits Convention. The (10 pts)",
        "Third Section investigated citizens in this ruler’s country, many of whom were once involved in the Decembrist uprising. Succeeding Alexander I, for ten points, name this tsar who led Russia into the disastrous Crimean War."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Nicholas I of Russia or Nikolai I",
        "Nikolai Pavlovich Romanov"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This city names an 1802 poem that opens with a cry for one of its native sons, “thou shouldst be living at this hour.” A poem about this city that opens “I wander thro’ each charter’d street” and describes hearing “how the (20 pts)",
        "Chimney-sweepers cry” was written by William Blake. A long poem about this “grand imperial town” was written by a man who uttered the quip “when a man is tired of [this city], he is tired of life” and wrote a (10 pts)",
        "Dictionary of the English Language, Samuel Johnson. For ten points, name this city whose modern squalor was captured in T.S. Eliot’s The Waste Land, including its heavily polluted Thames River."
      ],
      "answer": "London"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man initially refused to attend the Lancaster House peace talks after splitting with a faction led by Reverend Sithole. This man’s government massacred Ndebele civilians as part of the (20 pts)",
        "Gukurahundi. This man was opposed by the MDC party which was led by Morgan Tsvangirai. In 1987, this man absorbed Joshua Nkomo’s (10 pts)",
        "ZAPU party into this own ZANU party. This man was ousted after a power struggle between his wife Grace and vice-president Emmerson Mnangagwa. Extreme hyperinflation occurred under the leadership of, for ten points, what former dictator of Zimbabwe?"
      ],
      "answer": "Robert Mugabe"
    }
  ]
}